Sebastien VARRETTE, PhD

Research Associate

specialized in Distributed Platforms Security and HPC/Cloud systems.

14 years of experience in Linux HPC systems

 $\begin{array}{c} {\rm Phone:} \ +33(0)6 \ 74 \ 57 \ 90 \ 05 \\ {\rm E\text{-}mail:} \ {\rm Sebastien.Varrette@uni.lu} \end{array}$



Born on November 27th, 1979 (in France) Married (2004), two children (2007,2010)

Technical / Management

Main research domains:

EXPERTISE:

High Performance Computing (HPC) , Grid, Cluster & Cloud Platforms.

I'm administrating cluster-based HPC systems since 2003 (Linux environment)

Leader of an expert team of HPC system administrator since 2008. Security and Evaluation of Distributed Computing Platforms

Relevant contributions per domains:

- Code Obfuscation , CERTICLOUD, a Cloud IaaS secure platform
- Crash/cheating faults analysis in grid platforms
- Performance & Energy efficiency of HPC/Cloud platforms
- Design of the authentication system of Grid'5000Developing security awareness by education

Education

2007	Ph.D. In Computer Science, with honours (Excellent/Outstanding University of Luxembourg (UL) & Institut National Polytechnique de Grenoble (INPG) Thesis: Security in Large Scale Distributed Systems: Authentication and Result Checking Advisors: Franck Leprévost (UL) & Jean-Louis Roch (INPG)			
2003	M.Sc. in Computer Science	with honours (TB/First Class)		
	Speciality: Cryptology, Security and Information Coding (Coding)	CSCI), rank: 1st		
	Institut National Polytechnique de Grenoble (INPG) & Uni	versity Joseph Fourier (UJF)		
2003	MASTER'S DEGREE IN ENGINEERING (Telecoms ENSIMAC	with honours $(B/2.1)$		
	Speciality: Computer Sciences and Telecommunications	rank: top 10%		
1997 - 2000	Advanced Mathematics and Physics studies			
	For the competitive entrance to the French engineering s	chools		
1997	SCIENTIFIC "BACCALAURÉAT" (French "A" levels)	with honours $(B/2.1)$		

Employment

2011 - now	Research Associate (UL, Luxembourg)
2007 - 2010	SCIENTIFIC COLLABORATOR (UL, Luxembourg)
2004 - 2007	Research Assistant (UL, Luxembourg)
2003	System administrator (ID-IMAG, Grenoble, France)

Teaching Experience

2008 - now	Parallel & Grid Computing, Middleware	Master MICS2 (UL)
2004 - 2007	Programming Techniques I	Bachelor I1/CUT1 (UL)
	Advanced Programming in C, C++ and Java	Bachelor I2 (UL)
	System Administration and Network Security	Master CSCI2 (UJF)
2006	CRYPTOLOGY AND NETWORK SECURITY	, ,
	Master in Computer Science (Univ. of Yaoundé I. Cameroon)	

Additional Information

Languages	French (native language), English (fluent) and German (basic knowledge)
Sports	Karate (Black belt – 2nd DAN, Federal Instructor Diploma (DIF)), Jogging, Badminton, Ski etc.

Graduate Students Supervision

PhD.	Jakub Muszyński (2011 – 2015) Algorithms in Desktop Grids and V Benoît Bertholon (2010 – 2013)	Cheating-Tolerance of Parallel and Distributed Evolutionary Volunteer Computing Systems CertiCloud & JShadObf: Toward Integrity and Software
	Protection in Cloud Computing Pla	9 •
Master	MAXIME SCHMITT (2014–2015)	RESIF and OpenStack Deployment
	LUDOVIC SCHOEPPS (2014)	Design a REST API service to Monitor UL HPC Resources
	Anna Giannakou (2013)	Energy Efficiency in HPC environments
	Valentin Plugaru (2012 –)	Energy Efficiency of Hypervisors and Cloud middleware
	Sébastien Martinez (2012)	Source Code Obfuscation by mean of Evolutionary Algorithms
	Fotis Georgatos $(2012 - 2014)$	System administrator of the UL HPC facility
	Mateusz Guzek (2011)	System administration of cluster-based HPC systems
	Benoît Bertholon (2009)	Integrity issues in distributed executions
	CHRISTOPHE WEIS (2009)	Optimizing hash functions and S-Box by GEP
	Dominic Dunlop $(2008 - 2009)$	Using GAs to tune benchmarks for HPCs
	Romain Cavagna (2007 – 2008)	Deployment of a GForge platform
Bachelor	Hyacinthe Cartiaux (2011 –)	System administrator of the UL HPC facility
	Bernard Reichert (2008)	Collision detection implementation using CUDA

Research Projects

2007 - now	UL HPC, co-PI (UL cumulative contribution: 6.4 M€)
2014 - now	EU COST ACTION IC1305: Network for Sustainable Ultrascale Computing (NESUS)
2016 - 2019	co-PI, UL LSDEM (UL contribution: 332 k€)
2011 - 2013	UL EvoPerf (UL contribution: 373 k€)
2010 - 2012	FNR CORE GREENIT (Total: 1,5 M€, FNR contribution: 432 k€)
2010 - 2012	AFR PhD Bertholon (PHD-09-142; Scientific Advisor; Total/AFR contribution: 110 k€)
	Confidentiality and Integrity Issues over Cloud Computing Platforms
2009 - 2013	EU COST ACTION IC0804: Energy efficiency in large scale distributed systems
2009 - 2013	EU CoreGrid
2006 - 2008	ANR SAFESCALE-BGPR (ANR-05-SSIA-0005; ANR contribution: 68 k€)
2005 - now	GRID'5000 (technical committee)
2005 - 2007	FNR-SECOM TESEGRAD (FNR contribution: 300 k€)
2004 - 2007	CRYPTALPES
2004 - 2006	RAGTIME (Total: 545 k€, Rhône-Alpes Region contribution: 217 k€)

Professional Development

	IEEE Computer and Computational Intelligence society member Organizer of various conferences "Autorisation à Diriger des Recherches" (ADR) granted on July, 2015
2009 - now 2007 - now	TECHNICAL ADVISOR for LCSB and the MECO Ministry on HPC projects UL HPC Manager. Cumulative Project Investment: 6.3 M \in (as of 2015). 400 computing nodes, 4284 cores, $R_{\rm peak} = 49.92$ TFlops 150 servers (74,6% are Xen VMs) NFS, GPFS, Lustre Storage (Total capacity: 4268 TB) Management of a team of 4 system administrators
2007 - now 2006 2005 2005 - 2006 2005 - 2006 2000 - 2002	Manager of various IT services (Gforge @ Uni.lu, Jabber etc.) EGIDE mission for 3 weeks in Cameroon (master lecture – Univ. of Yaoudé I) EDITORIAL COMMITTEE for the definition of new UL master and bachelor degrees EDITORIAL COMMITTEE, UL website (CMS selection & management) FACULTY COUNCIL, elected member (assistant representative) ENSIMAG JUNIOR ENTERPRISE, developer member

Publication category	Quantity
PhD Thesis	1
Books	4
Magazine	1
Book Chapters	9
International journals	7
International conferences with proceedings and reviews	43
(French) national conferences with proceedings and reviews	4
International conferences with proceedings	1
International conferences with reviews	7
Masters Thesis	1
Technical Reports	8
Miscellaneous	1
Total:	87

Publish	Papers:117	Citations:330, Years:13	h-index:10,g-index:15	hc-index:8,hI-index:2,78,hI-norm:5	
or Perish	Cites/year: 25.38	Cites/paper: $2.95/1.0/0$	Cites/author: 113.24	Papers/author: 40.16	Query date: 2016-04-05
DBLP	Google Scholar				

Selected Publications